Hey there, it's true that preparing for diagrams
is the hardest among all types in Task 1.
Even popular guidebooks could just give a few tips and knowledge for diagrams.
But with years of experience handling diagrams,
I'll show you the most effective way to handle this challenging question.
Our lesson is divided into three parts.
Part 1, Diagrams, Analysis and Outlining.
Part 2, Diagrams, Linking Devices.
And part 3, Diagrams, Sample Evaluation.
And since then, we will find a way to improve it.
To achieve two goals.
Understand how to analyse diagrams, select and organise information from there.
Understand how to make a complete outline based on question analysis.
I don't know about you guys, but I'm excited about this.
Are you with me?
Let's go.
Let's have a quick overview of this type.
Diagram, Process or Flowchart.
It may have a different name depending on the specific form.
However, they all require us to describe a process, a certain structure or an operating procedure.
So how many types of diagrams do you think there are?
There are two common types of diagrams.
How something works or how something is made
and a natural process.
In this lesson, we will analyse the process
of making cherry jam to understand the general approach.
Do you still remember the three steps to
analyse charts in task 1 that we've been
familiar with up to now?
They are the big three, the great three
and the major three.
Let's apply these three steps to our writing question today.
The diagram describes the process of making cherry jam.
Summarise the information by selecting and reporting
the main features and make comparisons where relevant.
Here's my outline.
Please pause the video to read through it.
Now let's go through each step one by one to see how to get such an outline.
Let's start with the big three.
What and where commercial manufacturing of cherry jam
at a processing plant?
When.
Time is not given so we will use present tenses.
Most diagram questions use the present simple
because they describe a general truth or a repeat process.
Since this is a series of actions,
we use the simple tense throughout.
Unit none.
Diagrams have no units so you can leave this blank.
For the great three, subject of comparison none.
Diagrams also have no subjects of comparison so just fill in none.
Global feature number one.
Since there are no trends, let's look for two global features.
Some students have read some samples and
concluded that the overview of diagrams writing only needs to state
how many steps are involved, but that's not true.
The purpose of the overview is to evaluate
your overall understanding.
If it just states the number of steps
in one sentence, anyone can do it just by looking at the diagram.
So how can examiners evaluate us?
Simple overviews like that are likely to score
band five or lower for task achievement.
So what's the correct way then?
Here's my suggestion.
Let's focus on the following two pieces of information.
One, the first information related to the nature
of the diagram, whether the process is simple or complex with a clear result at the end,
following a linear or cyclical path.
How many sections or stages there are and
list the key information if possible.
From there, we have the first global feature,
a linear process consisting of two major phases,
fruit preparation and jam production.
Global feature two should mention how many steps
from what to what and the most significant difference
if asked to compare different things.
We have global feature two, nine steps in total,
beginning with the harvesting of raw cherries
and ending with the labelling of finished jars.
We always have a complete outline for all diagrams questions.
However, to get that outline, we need to
go through three elements, starting with grouping information.
There are many ways to group information in diagrams,
depending on each specific question.
It's hard to say there's a general method
that can be applied to all diagrams, but
you can follow three popular ways.
They are grouping by step, divide paragraphs based on the steps of the diagram.
We'll look at the whole diagram and find out
the step that shows a significant change
in the input material, like changing into a
completely new form or the step that marks
the end of a stage in the process
and use that as the point of division.
Grouping by section, divide paragraphs based on different parts,
sections or contents of the diagram.
Grouping by diagram, this technique can be applied
to handling questions with more than one diagram.
Alright, now let's move on to the major
three, individual features.
Unlike other question types where specific details and
figures need to be selected for description,
with diagrams we will describe all steps and stages presented,
leaving no detail behind.
Remember to use the passive voice
if the subject of the action is not specified.
Even after doing so, the writing may still
be short and doesn't meet the requirement of
word count.
Therefore, to ensure the length and also to
improve the task achievement score, for some steps
we need to provide reason or purpose of that step.
If there are other reasons or purposes,
each step will be analysed in more detail and sentences will also be longer.
Please note to do this instead of just listing out all the steps.
Lastly, detail organisation.
With diagrams, you don't need to worry much about arranging ideas.
Just describe each step one by one and
you'll have a complete outline like this.
It's time to apply the knowledge we've learned
to evaluate the sample.
I believe you're all familiar with this step,
but to make sure, let me remind you a bit.
Please spend 10 minutes evaluating the task achievement
and coherence and cohesion of the sample based on
5 guiding questions.
1. Is the sample divided into paragraphs?
2. Are they complete paragraphs?
3. Is there an overview and does it play its role correctly?
4. Does the sample provide all important details and data?
5. Is there cohesion within sentences and between paragraphs?
And are cohesive devices used correctly?
Please pause the video in 10 minutes and evaluate the sample.
Then come back to the lesson and listen to the explanation.
I'll see you in 10 minutes.
There shouldn't be much to complain about
the paragraphing of the sample, if the whole body
is not written in only one paragraph.
Each contains at least two sentences, which is good,
but the body should be divided into
two paragraphs, corresponding to the two stages that we've analysed.
However, even if we do so, the sample
cannot have a high score, due to the lack of words.
It already looks short, not enough to reach 130 words.
Although there is an overview, it's not very effective, because it is unclear.
Just listing steps makes it hard to surpass band 5.
The main reason for lacking words and leading
to the low task achievement score is because
the writer just listed the steps in the
diagram without analysing them, providing reasons or purposes.
The process consists of only 5 steps, making it difficult to avoid lacking information.
Even for diagrams with 14 to 15 steps,
writing like this may not reach the required 150 words.
So the analysis of this sample is completely ineffective.
Finally, about linking devices.
We don't see the use of languages of sequencing to connect steps.
Very few devices are used, mostly just the basic word AND.
I hope that while writing, you will apply
what we've learned today to avoid these mistakes
and improve your task achievement and coherence and
cohesion scores to band 6+.
See, diagrams won't be a challenge if we
follow the right direction and understand the knowledge.
By now, we've got the steps to
effectively analyse this type of question and create a complete outline.
About the big 3, most diagrams use the present tense.
If there's any information about before, it should be described in the past tense.
And remember, there are no units.
About the great 3, there are no subjects
of comparison, and two global features often focus on two pieces of information.
1. Simple or complex, linear or cyclical, how many
stages or sections.
And 2. How many steps, from what to what,
and the most significant difference.
Getting into details about the major 3,
there are many ways to group information in diagrams depending on each question, but there are three common ways.
Grouping by step, grouping by section, and grouping by diagram.
Next, about individual features, don't forget to provide
reasons or purposes to analyse some steps more deeply.
If you follow these steps, I'm sure your scores will be high.
Take detailed notes, organise them, fill out the
do's and don'ts checklist, and complete all the homework.
Your scores will be even better.
In the next lessons, we'll learn about useful
language and grammar structures to describe diagrams more effectively.
So don't worry too much, because there's always a solution to any difficulty.
Now it's time to take a break and
get ready for the next challenges.
Keep up the good work!
I'm Anna, goodbye and see you next time.